Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
We wish Your Majesty good health and eternal blessings.
I haven't seen Lady Sourire for some time.
Raise your head and let me look at you.
All rise.
We thank Your Majesty.
Lady Sourire not only has good manners
but also a gentle nature.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Allow me to kneel to greet Your Majesty.
I rejoice at seeing Your Majesty.
Very well. You are well-mannered indeed.
I am young and unschooled.
Blessed by Your Majesty's grace
and the teachings from Her Majesty and the other concubines,
I have not behaved improperly.
No wonder the emperor likes you. I like you, too.
-Bamboo.
-Yes.
Get two pieces of cloud brocade for Lady Sourire.
I am grateful to Your Majesty.
Can you write?
Lady Sourire is highly educated and
well versed in poetry and history.
I have inadequately studied poetry and history.
But my handwriting may be too inferior
to be of any use to Your Majesty.
It's good that you can write.
When you have time,
come here and copy some sutras for me.
If Your Majesty is not troubled by my coarseness,
it will be my great pleasure to serve Your Majesty.
You've been here one day after another.
Now you have less time to yourself.
I am honored to copy sutras for Your Majesty.
Heavy snow broke the tree branches in the courtyard.
But you were able to write in peace.
I find that you're very quiet in general.
My mind wasn't at peace, but copying
sutras for Your Majesty calmed my mind.
Nothing brings more peace than the words of the Buddha.
Have you finished?
Almost.
Your Majesty also likes sandalwood?
I burn it as an offering the Buddha.
It's rarely used in the harem.
How do you recognize the incense?
I light it for myself sometimes.
It's more calming than benzoin resin.
That's right. Life has its ups and downs.
I'm glad you know how to put your mind at peace.
I said I'm coming tonight. Why did you go to bed early?
Are you tired from copying the sutras?
I'm not that delicate.
I was just feeling cold and sleepy waiting for Your Majesty.
I lost track of time when I was going through the memorandums.
It's my fault.
It's cold and snowy tonight. I thought Your Majesty
would go to Her Majesty's palace since it's close by.
I just stayed at the Palace of Great Benevolence the day before.
Why are you telling me to go again?
It's cold recently and Her Majesty is busy at the year end.
Her Majesty might be feeling under the weather.
Your Majesty should spend more time with her.
When I paid my respects to Her Majesty yesterday,
I saw her new painting of the winter plums.
Has Your Majesty seen it yet?
I haven't.
I will have lunch with her tomorrow and have a look.
Her Majesty would put a great deal of effort into a midday meal..
Perhaps Your Majesty could have dinner with Her Majesty instead?
Then Your Majesty will able to stay at the Palace of Great Benevolence.
My Huan Huan is so generous.
Her Majesty is the mother of the country.
Your Majesty should spend more time with her.
That's a very kind request. I will go tomorrow.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise. Have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
What is going on today?
Everyone arrived almost at the same time as if it was planned.
How coincidental!
It's very cold lately. Have you been feeling better?
I feel much better. Thank you for asking.
Excuse me.
It was just a cold,
but it's taking me so long to get over it.
Did anyone notice?
Because of the cold, Attendant An's voice is not as beautiful as before.
Sourire only cares about An.
You were ignoring me. I'm your sister too.
Yes, yes you are.
Everyone is a sister to one another here.
Sourire, look, I put on some weight again.
I've outgrown clothes that were just recently made.
I'm not surprised. Two bowls of porridge
and three sugar buns for breakfast.
Succulent chicken and duck for lunch.
Snacks before dinner.
If I didn't stop you, you would have devoured the entire
pot of ham and pigs feet at dinner.
Yet you were still hungry and shouting for late night snacks.
I'm more concerned about your swelling
stomach than the swelling food expenses.
You are always making fun of me!
But you are right,
I must stop eating like this.
His Majesty said they have to make
new clothes for me every two months.
I'm either getting taller or bigger.
I wish I could be like An.
She's so thin.
There's nothing wrong with gaining a little weight.
As long as His Majesty likes it.
Rather, Attendant An is jealous that you have a healthy appetite.
Lingrong, you are slim and delicate.
In addition to your medicine, you should eat more nourishing food.
I thank Your Majesty.
I'm not as fortunate as Chun'er.
She's fortunate to have a good appetite,
and to be cared for.
Chun'er, Sourire cares about you so much.
She remembers everything you eat.
All right, take a seat.
Yes.
Lady Fuca, are you all right?
Did you eat something unclean?
Your Majesty, My Lady didn't eat unclean food.
My Lady is with child.
Nonsense.
Is it true? That's wonderful news!
We all need to congratulate His Majesty.
You're with child?
Was it confirmed by an imperial doctor?
Two doctors have confirmed it.
I'm not the type who would stoop to anything
to gain His Majesty's favor.
Yes means yes, no means no.
Why would I lie about an imperial heir?
Isn't Companion Shen's example enough?
Lady Sourire, don't you agree?
Lady Fuca is truly blessed.
She had good news very quickly.
I recall His Majesty has been busy recently.
His Majesty only visited you every
few months and you got pregnant.
How blessed you are!
Indeed, this is a blessing bestowed by Heaven.
[Heaven also refers to an emperor]
They say it could be a prince.
Attendant Joie, what do you think?
Heaven determines whether it is a boy or a girl.
The fortune of conceiving a prince does not land on everyone.
All right, a girl is as good as a boy.
Lady Fuca, you must take care of your health when bearing an imperial heir.
There mustn't be any oversights.
I thank your Majesty.
Noble Lady Sourire!
There's something my dull-witted mind cannot comprehend.
I wish to ask you a question.
I am all ears.
I am full of pity for you.
To be honest, you are the most favored
and the most visited concubine of His Majesty.
How do you still not have good news for us?
Now that Lady Fuca is with child,
His Majesty will pay more attention to her.
You will have more time to yourself, and
should improve your reproductive health.
Lady Fuca bears His Majesty's child.
Naturally he will spend more time with her.
Thank you for caring about my health.
But surely Princess Wenyi's health is your top priority.
The princess is more precious than gold.
No harm must come to her.
Thank you.
Noble Lady Cao has verbally offended Your Highness.
I entreat Your Highness's forgiveness for her.
What?
Lady Cao just said that I am most frequently visited
by His Majesty but not pregnant.
Her words of mockery also apply to Your Highness.
Of all His Majesty's concubines,
Your Highness has been visited the most.
Hence I beg Your Highness's pardon on Cao's behalf.
What is the big deal about being pregnant?
Your Highness...
I will have a son if Heaven blesses me.
If not, I will have a daughter.
It's better than not having any.
I agree with Your Highness.
His Majesty's favor is not dependent on bearing a heir.
The belief that a concubine can gain favor by having a child
is only true if His Majesty cares about the child.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
You are still awake, My Lady.
It's late. You should rest.
Lady Fuca got pregnant easily after few times of service.
But I ...
haven't have any luck.
I have to say I'm not as blessed as her.
How come?
My Lady, you have Heaven's great blessing.
Having good news is just a matter of time.
All you need to do is wait patiently.
Today, the palace guards told me that
there is a plague spreading in the city.
It's possible that it will affect the palace.
You must take extra caution, My Lady.
Have a good rest.
I asked Songzhi to send some mountain yam cakes to Lady Fuca.
But she said she was pregnant and couldn't stand up to thank me.
How dare she!
Lady Fuca was brash, but it doesn't mean
she disrespects Your Highness.
She became so full of herself right after she conceived!
When she gives birth her arrogance over her increased status will be sky-high!
Not necessarily. Concort Astuce [Third Prince's mother] is an example.
Lady Fuca is young and pretty. Her favor from
His Majesty will outlast the older concubines.
Indeed.
It won't be too much of a concern if she has a princess.
But if she gives birth to a prince ...
It's been a long time since the last prince was born ...
His Majesty would rejoice greatly ...
I recall His Majesty only visited you one time this month.
Now that Lady Fuca is pregnant,
I'm afraid you'll go from one to zero.
I only wish for Wenyi to have good health and a peaceful life.
You can tolerate others, but they might not tolerate you.
Fortunately, Lady Fuca is not the blessed kind.
A plague broke out in the city when she got pregnant.
His Majesty is very concerned about it.
Your Highness, the plague has reached the palace.
What?
Have you distributed dried mugwort to each palace?
Yes, Your Majesty. We did it overnight.
Lady Fuca is pregnant.
Send extra to her palace.
The Palace of Earthly Honor was the first
to report a carrier of the plague.
Her palace must be completely cleansed.
Burn mugwort leaves in her palace to dispel the disease
every dawn, noon, and dusk.
In addition, the Imperial Infirmary must prepare medicinal herbs
for the maids in every palace to make sachets tonight.
Everyone needs to wear the sachets and put them in their rooms.
Yes.
- Dr Zhang.
- Yes.
You are the head of the Imperial Infirmary.
What's your understanding of the plague?
This disease is caused by an external pathogen.
It starts with a fever and headache,
and then progresses into severe blood stasis.
One sick person will infect the entire chamber,
and one chamber, the entire palace.
It is better to take preventive measures
as early as possible before it becomes prevalent.
Is it that serious?
I dare not make an overstatement before Your Majesty.
A servant in the harem has already contracted the plague.
It's coming aggressively from the city!
The Imperial Infirmary will take early precautions.
I request Your Majesty to inform the harem
to avoid making unnecessary trips and visits.
The palace is already in panic after
hearing about the presence of the plague.
They will strictly obey your instructions, Dr Zhang.
I trust the Imperial Infirmary will work hard on it.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Highness, the servant Xiao-Dezi
in our palace contracted the plague.
The Household Department is going to move him out.
Immediately!
Burn everything he has used and worn.
Smash his pots and cups.
Scatter lime in his room to dispel bad fortune.
Your Highness need not worry.
I have already told the servants to do it.
How can I not worry?
Peace to Your Highness.
Your Highness, Her Majesty said that
the plague has emerged in the palace,
which requires Your Highness’s assistance.
Boiling liquor [a disinfectant] has been doused in the Eastern Six Palaces.
And mugwort leaves are being burned.
The Western six palaces are entrusted to Your Highness.
All right.
Her Majesty also mentioned that although the
Palace of Universal Happiness has fewer occupants,
Companion Shen’s Chamber of Chrysanthemums
must be opened to burn mugwort leaves.
Not a palace in the harem should be overlooked.
Tell Her Majesty I will do it properly.
Allow me to take my leave
Liu Ben escaped.
Shen still remains a menace to me.
But if Companion Shen is dead ...
the dead tell no tales even if Liu Ben is caught.
We failed in getting Shen Meizhuang the death penalty.
She got very lucky.
Now we shall let her perish.
Is there any thing in Xiao-Dezi’s room of use to us?
Err ...
There is a tea set that he has been using.
If it was unknowingly used for tea,
the person would definitely be infected.
It’s a waste to smash a nice tea set.
Send it to the Chamber of Chrysanthemums.
Understood.
His Majesty cares for you, My Lady,
and ordered us to clean up your chamber.
We hope to protect you from the plague, My Lady.
I seek your forgiveness for any inconveniences.
Mind your own work and I will I fend for myself .
There is no inconvenience.
Yes, My Lady.
Scatter some liquor outside.
Come in.
My Lady, the Household Department sends you a new tea set
since your utensils are not in good condition.
The tea has been made for you, My Lady.
Thank you.
My Lady,
We have almost finished the work outside.
I have to go to the other palaces if you allow me.
I bid you goodbye, My Lady.
You have been coughing lately.
Make sure you take extra care of yourself.
Thank you.
Thank you, My Lady.
We are burning mugwort leaves three times a day as required.
The Imperial Infirmary sent some medical sachets .
I took some more for you since you've been feeling unwell.
The Palace of Pearl Jade is well provided for
since you and Attendant Chun live there.
What are these ?
The Imperial Infirmary sent some Bai Zhu root
to be burned with the mugwort.
This basket is for the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Oh, put them all in my chamber.
This is for everyone in the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Why didn't Attendant An receive any?
I beg your pardon, Lady Fuca.
You must give some to Attendant An.
Attendant An is strong and healthy.
She doesn't need this.
I am with His Majesty's child.
I need to be treated with more care.
I will surely give priority to Attendant An when she is pregnant.
Lady Fuca, you and your child's health matter.
So does Attendant An's.
The Imperial Infirmary will keep sending the herbs.
Why would you have all of them to yourself?
Ah I see, in the presence of Lady Sourire,
Attendant An finds the courage to argue for things.
Fuca, you misunderstood. I didn't intend to.
Attendant An has a good temper.
But I have to say this for her.
What happens in my palace is what I say.
You are welcome to tell His Majesty if you disagree.
I believe His Majesty will give priority to an imperial heir.
You don't need to involve His Majesty to make sense of this.
If you use all the Bai Zhu root,
and Attendant An then contracts the disease, won't your own palace be at more risk?
Are you cursing me ?
You will be in trouble when I tell His Majesty.
It's up to you whether you should tell His Majesty.
I'm afraid His Majesty will agree that
you are not thinking of the greater good.
I'm not going to listen to you.
Move them in.
And shut the door
Sourire, don't waste your breath and cause yourself trouble.
I know it was pointless.
But if I don't speak up for you,
she will do this time after time.
That will upset you again and again.
Let's go back to the room.
I will ask the Imperial Infirmary for some Bai Zhu.
It is not that easy.
I would not contend with her if it was easily available.
Let's go.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
How many people died today?
Already two this morning.
The plague is spreading ferociously.
Even the Imperial Infirmary hasn't a clue what to do.
His Majesty, Her Majesty, Consort Fleur, and Consort Astuce,
have been praying for two days in the Baohua Hall.
The plague has spread all over the city.
The imperial doctors are "a cup of water on a burning carriage".
His Majesty has lost weight after a few days of anxiety.
Such a pungent smell.
It is. The maids have been boiling
vinegar to prevent the spread of the plague.
It makes the palace smell unpleasant.
I have got used to the smell.
My Lady, terrible news!
Inform My Lady calmly.
The Palace of Universal Happiness reported that
Lady Meizhuang contracted the plague.
My Lady, don't go!
How did this happen?
Take it easy, Sourire. Have a seat.
She was all right yesterday.
But this morning, Orchid reported that
she vomited all that she ate
and developed a high fever.
And she began to talk deliriously since noon.
What about the imperial doctors? Did they come?
Forget about the doctors.
Companion Shen has long been neglected in her confinement.
The plague is very contagious.
Who dares to go?
I've sent for doctors a few times.
But no one visited.
Sourire, what should we do?
I've tried my best.
I wanted to ask His Majesty for help,
but he has been at court all morning.
The Empress Dowager, the Empress, and the consorts
are all praying in the Baohua Hall.
There's no one who can order the doctors to come.
I will go see her.
- You mustn't go, My Lady.
- Don't go, My Lady.
Sourire, it's dangerous to go into her chamber.
The disease is infectious.
I can't decide for her before I see her.
My Lady...
My Lady!
My Lady, I know you are worried about Lady Meizhuang.
But you must also care for yourself.
Exactly.
You should just look from behind the door.
I'm going in for one glance. Just one quick look.
My Lady, don't.
Lady Meizhuang is already infected.
You have to protect yourself.
Just one glance.
Otherwise there would be no one
to speak for Lady Meizhuang.
Please look after her, Madam.
Mr Su.
I hope you can understand, My Lady.
The plague is rampant in the city.
His Majesty is anxious and discussing it with his ministers.
His Majesty can't spare a minute right now.
How much longer will the discussions take?
It's a serious matter. I can't speculate on that.
If it is very urgent, My Lady,
you should go see the Empress first.
I'm afraid I should not.
I can't see Her Majesty without His Majesty's permission.
Is this about Companion Shen?
You'd better not, My Lady.
If you would listen to me, My Lady,
His Majesty has been distressed over the plague.
You should not mention Companion Shen
and add to His Majesty's stress.
You should consider other solutions.
Thank you, sir.
But please inform His Majesty when you have a chance.
Yes, My Lady.
Wen Shichu bows before Lady Sourire.
Please rise, Dr Wen.
Thank you, My Lady.
May I speak to you privately?
Dr Wen, are you still occupied with the treatment of the plague?
I am.
Would you be willing to help me if I ask for a favor?
To be frank with you, sir,
helping me will not bring you any recognition,
and may result in serious punishment if others find out.
But my heart will never rest easy if I don't ask.
My Lady, will it ease your mind if I am willing to do it?
If you help me, sir, my mind will be at peace.
For that, My Lady, I will do everything I can.
I'm at your disposal.
Companion Shen contracted the plague in the Chamber of Chrysanthemums.
Her life is at stake.
I'm asking you to help her.
But ...
she is a concubine in solitary confinement.
No matter who she is, I will do what you ask me to
if that will bring peace to your mind.
Thank you, Dr Wen.
Allow me to take my leave, My Lady.
Dr Wen.
Please take care.
Five maces of Dong'e ejiao...
His Majesty didn't even have
the appetite to eat because of the plague.
You must find the cure without delay!
Yes, Your Highness.
Your Highness must be patient.
We have never had a prescription for an epidemic like this.
We are like "the blind men and an elephant" - groping slowly.
Slowly?
I can't bear to see His Majesty so anxious.
We are trying our best.
Are you? You've been searching the books for days.
What have you found?
I might as well read this myself!
Your Highness has stayed up for nights.
We would be held responsible should Your Highness feel unwell.
Dr.Wen, you should go rest.
The prescription is almost completed.
Sir, you have been working hard day and night on the plague formula.
I have to be faithful to a promise.
Work is not hard but duty.
Yes.
Dr. Wen is still here. You have been working hard.
Dr. Jiang.
Dr. Wen, you have to take care of the concubines during the day,
and pursue the remedy for the plague at night.
You must be exhausted.
Did you make any progress on the prescription?
Not yet.
But I will do my best.
I’ll go now since you’re busy.
After Lady Meizhuang was infected with the plague,
the guards were afraid to get close to her and thus slacking.
I have secretly sent Dr. Wen into her chamber.
How are Lunar and Stellar?
They are very conscientious ...
Lady Meizhuang is not improving because Dr. Wen is treating her in secret,
so he can't order all the herbs or the nourishing food she needs to get well.
But I'm afraid that's all we can do for now.
Yes, My Lady.
Congratulation, My Lady! Your wish came true.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
How serious is the plague in the palace now?
Your Majesty, the servants died one after another.
The palace is in a panic.
If so, it must be much worse outside the palace.
Yes, I heard that all the wealthy families
tried to escape town
only to see the suburbs full of infected citizens.
So they were frightened and came back.
I’ve heard that the city itself isn't the most affected area.
The village in Yongping is more afflicted.
Yes, the villagers were locked up in quarantine
as soon as they showed symptoms of the plague.
The detainees had no way out but death.
Lady Sourire requests an audience with Your Majesty.
At this time of the night?
It must be something urgent, Your Majesty.
- Show her in.
- Yes, Your Majesty.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
What happened? Is it very urgent?
You can go now.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Go ahead.
Xiao-Yunzi.
You don't raise your head before His Majesty?
Liu Ben bows in respect before Your Majesty.
Why are you here?
I never believed that Companion Shen
would feign pregnancy to gain favor.
So I secretly began to search for Liu Ben.
They finally found him at
the border of Yongzhou, Hunan Province.
The maid Poria was flogged to death.
But Liu Ben was taking care of Companion Shen all along.
He is the only one who knows exactly what happened to Shen.
I won’t force confession under torture.
But if you dare to tell a word of untruth,
I will make you suffer more than death.
I heard that when he was found, he was
disguised as a beggar to avoid being discovered.
Dr Liu, you don't have to tell us anything.
But if you do so, I will send you out of the palace right away.
I bet they will cut off your head
before you can leave Beijing.
If you still choose not to tell the truth,
you are digging your own grave.
Your Majesty, Lady Meizhuang was never pregnant.
That I know.
But Lady Meizhuang didn't know that herself.
When she was in "prenatal care",
her menstruation had stopped.
And her symptoms -- dizziness and
vomiting - were caused by medication, not pregnancy.
But before I took her pulse, I was ordered
to diagnose her with pregnancy regardless.
You were ordered? By whom?
By …
She is going to kill you.
Why are you hesitant to say her name?
Consort Fleur. It was Consort Fleur.
If you have told a single word of untruth ...
I dare not, Your Majesty, I dare not.
I know I have committed a capital offense.
Consort Fleur gave me a sum of money,
and told me to leave the Summer Palace
at once to avoid trouble.
She assured me that I would be
aided when I got back to the city.
But as soon as I entered the city,
there were killers chasing after me all the way.
I was running around for life like a homeless dog.
Xiao-Yunzi, take him out and keep him under close watch.
Don't let anything happen.
Yes, My Lady.
Come with me.
May peace be restored in Your Majesty.
Is it possible that ... he has not told the entire truth?
There is much doubt over
what happened to Companion Shen.
But we have no evidence.
In hindsight, if Shen menstruated a few days before,
why would she have her stained clothing
discarded right in Your Majesty's presence?
Also, Companion Shen mentioned that Dr. Jiang
had given her a prescription to help with pregnancy.
But it went missing right when we were looking for it.
If the prescription never existed,
wouldn't it have been very stupid of Shen to mention it?
I’m afraid Your Majesty has the same doubts.
I saw that prescription before.
It didn't seem improper to me.
Consort Fleur.
Very well.
That prescription to prove Meizhuang's
innocence was probably stolen.
That maid called Poria...
She must be involved in this.
I flogged Poria to death that day out of unrestrained rage.
If only I interrogated her instead.
Your Majesty's is not to blame.
Poria must have been determined to ruin Companion Shen
since she dared to defame her.
But now ...
What will Your Majesty do?
I wronged Meizhuang.
I will let her out and restore her title.
I'm afraid it's too late.
Did she ...
No, Meizhuang didn't have any suicidal thoughts.
But contracted the plague due to depression and weakened Qi.
There's was nothing for her to worry over.
Confinement may have been the only punishment imposed.
But because she fell from grace,
all the servants in the palace disdain her.
I will send imperial doctors to treat Lady Vertu immediately.
I won't let anything happen to her.
I beg Your Majesty's forgiveness for my offence.
When I saw she was seriously ill,
I secretly asked an imperial doctor to take care of her.
You did?
I seek Your Majesty's pardon.
Had you not risked your life to safe hers,
I would have been in eternal regret for Lady Vertu.
Your Majesty did nothing wrong.
The sly evildoer "clouded your wisdom eyes".
Consort Fleur fooled me into this ...
I won't forgive her.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Bring my order to the Imperial Infirmary:
Jiang Cheng and Jiang Sheng are granted suicide.
Consort Fleur is deprived of her
honorary name and demoted to Noble Lady.
Wait.
Deprived of her honorary name and demoted to Concubine.
Your Majesty, the deprivation of honorary name is
a greater punishment than demotion.
What made Your Majesty so upset?
Go to the Palace of Universal Happiness first ...
Declare that I have restored Lady Vertu's status and honorary name.
Her health takes priority.
Yes.
But it's very late now.
If the Household Department delivers Your Majesty's decree now,
I'm afraid it will disturb the entire harem.
Then do it tomorrow.
Act as if nothing happened.
I understand.
I will go to the Palace of Universal Happiness now.
Huan Huan ...
Did you arrange Liu Ben to ...
What?
Nothing.
Does Your Majesty think I instructed Liu Ben to defame Consort Fleur?
Does Your Majesty think I'm that kind of person?
I dare not ...
I am too proud to do that.
If I had intended to save Lady Vertu and defame
Consort Fleur, I wouldn't have waited until today.
I wouldn't have waited until Lady Vertu's life is in peril.
If Your Majesty distrusts me,
Mr. Su can't have gotten far.
Your Majesty can revoke the decree.
I was being suspicious.
If I didn't believe you, I wouldn't have punished Consort Fleur.
If Your Majesty trusts me, Your Majesty wouldn't have asked that.
Huan Huan.
I misspoke.
It's all right. Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Consort Fleur has always been thorough and attentive in her service.
I thought she was just domineering sometimes,
but I'm really disappointed about what she did this time.
I understand, Your Majesty.
Great news for the Palace of
Universal Happiness and Lady Vertu.
His Majesty has lifted Lady Vertu's confinement.
Her title and rewards remain the same as before.
I'm grateful to His Majesty.
Congratulations.
Thank you, Mr. Su.
What a joyous moment of vindication!
Exactly.
But unfortunately, Lady Vertu cannot
hear the good news for herself.
Is she still unconscious?
Dr. Wen, My Lady's fever has broken.
But she vomited the medicine.
How much did she vomit?
About one third.
But I did follow the prescription for her symptoms.
Maybe the medicine was too strong.
I'll try to adjust the dosage.
Dr. Wen, is Lady Vertu feeling better?
A little bit.
But her illness was not promptly reported.
She is gravely ill and still unconscious.
Please allow me to some time to figure it out.
That's very kind of you, sir.
I heard that you have been here for over a day.
I will have a guilty conscience if I cannot cure My Lady.
For your tireless dedication, sir,
I will surely inform His Majesty to reward you.
My Lady, the plague is rampant in the palace.
Are we really going to visit Lady Meizhuang?
His Majesty reinstated Lady Vertu's title.
I'm afraid she is seriously ill.
But don't worry, the guards won't let us in.
We will just send our greetings outside.
Yes, My Lady.
Peace to Attendant An.
Mr. Xia, I'm here to visit Lady Vertu.
The imperial doctor is busy taking care of her.
I'm afraid it's not a convenient time, My Lady.
And since the plague is infectious,
you should stay away from here, My Lady.
Sir, may I trouble you to inform Lady Vertu that I visited?
I will, My Lady.
Do you know ... why His Majesty
reinstated Lady Vertu so suddenly?
Didn't Lady Sourire tell you, My Lady?
The culprit, Liu Ben was captured.
Really?
You don't have to believe me, My Lady.
You are His Majesty's direct servant.
I believe you.
The news was unexpected.
What a wonderful surprise!
Exactly, My Lady.
Someone will be in great trouble
now that Liu Ben has been caught.
Who?
I can't tell you now
because it would cause chaos in the palace.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.